hey everyone welcome back to this tosa
automation playlist and today we are
going to discuss about another
interesting topic or feature which is
provided by tosa and today uh I will
show you how you can basically compare
to Excel files which is a pretty common
scenario in any automation you perform
with any kind of application you always
have some data in Excel files right and
uh in order to compare them either you
can use some utilities provided by an
automation tool or you have to build
your own automation utility now in uh
tools like selenium uh you need to use
different libraries to basically access
uh or open or even compare the different
Excel files but uh tosa already provides
you with all of these uh in the standard
subset as a mod module okay so there are
different modules uh to access different
Excel files or you can also steer these
Excel files you can open them you can um
create entries or you can also save them
right so basically you can perform all
the things uh with respect to the Excel
files using this uh modules which are
present in the standard subset now this
is part of the Excel engine uh which is
present in tosa and then uh you can
perform all these different operations
using the different modules which are
present okay so today um I'm not going
to show you how you can steer Excel
files basically uh create or open Excel
files but I'm going to show you how you
can compare the Excel files maybe I will
show you uh in the next session um how
you can steer even uh all the different
Excel files
okay so uh to compare Excel files let's
take an example and see how we can do
this okay so I have already created a
test case for folder called Excel engine
and here uh I have created a test case
called compare Excel okay so the first
step is to get the tbox module okay uh
which is used for automation so um the
process is same you do a search and ADD
test step and then try to find for uh
tbox Excel um something related to tbox
excel right and that will give you the
whole list you can see here there are
lots of modules for uh creating Excel
workbook uh for deleting updating uh
closing opening right um Range
manipulation so all the different uh
things which you need to do or perform
uh during automation with respect to
Microsoft Excel sheets you can use this
different modules okay so we'll go
through all these different modules uh
but today we are looking at the tbox
Excel 1 is to one file compare okay so
this is the module uh which we are going
to use in order to compare to excel
sheets okay so uh you can either uh
compare all the sheets or you can
compare uh specific sheets right so
there are some parameters which you need
to fulfill okay before that so let's go
ahead and add this module
now and once you add this module you can
see there are different parameters as I
said okay for this or module attributes
for this particular module and you need
to provide a value or action mode
depending on what you want to perform
okay so the most uh important things uh
to put here is the reference file okay
so this is the file um which will be as
a reference point okay uh and against
this you will be comparing it with
another file okay which will be our
Target file uh you can also provide a
reference password the target password
if your file is password protected okay
uh then uh you can include uh
different cells data okay so you can
tell whether um you want to include uh
cells data you can include different
formats you can include different
objects you can include different sheets
okay so you can specify all this
information if you want to compare
specific cells specific format or
specific objects okay so uh in
this uh the most most important is the
include sheets part okay and then the
output part where you want to store your
results okay so if it's a failure it
will show you where the failure is
happening uh which rows are not matching
okay or if it is a pass uh it won't be
writing anything into the output path
okay so these are all the uh values
which you need to provide now looking at
the comparison so I have got two Excel
files here okay so here you can see uh
there is users and there is users one
okay mostly it contains the similar data
but I have changed one row you can see
here this test gmail.com is one row
which I have changed in both the sheets
it contains a list of different email
address the sheet name is email
okay and uh the similar thing is present
here except that one email address which
is not present here okay so currently my
Excel sheets are not matching and I want
to see whether tosa is able to compare
them and tell me that this uh is not
matching and tell me where it is not
matching okay what um what row is
missing from that particular sheet
right okay um so we need to provide the
reference file path so this will be our
reference file path users okay so I'm
going to copy this path here and put it
here so we'll say users uh you need to
also provide the EXT ension so it will
be xlsx okay and uh it will be the same
for Target except the name Will Change
we need to provide uh the target file
name here so it is users one and then um
I don't have any password I don't want
to um do this include CS data or format
or object it's pretty much optional uh
you can either provide it's a data type
is Boolean so you can provide true and
false here okay so it will include the
format it will include the sales data
and it will include the objects
okay uh but it's optional as I said here
most important thing is you can give the
sheet names if you have multiple sheets
okay you can give which sheet name you
want to include and which sheet name you
don't want to include okay so if you
don't provide the name here the sheet
name it will be excluded from the
comparison right so our sheet name is
email okay and um let's put a semicolon
here and then we need to provide a
output path okay so my output path is
this c training report inside this there
is a results file okay so I'm going to
give uh
results and then uh we have to also give
the extension we'll give txt okay so
here uh the results will be written
after this comparison is done okay so
it's pretty simple uh if you have got to
excel sheets you can just provide the
reference file path and the target file
path and the sheet names which you want
to compare and then the output path okay
so these are the things you need to give
in this particular tbox module now let's
go ahead and run this in scratchbook and
we'll see uh what is the comparison
result it will take a few seconds to
compare uh now it depends also on the
data you have in this Excel sheets um
and uh accordingly the time will be
taken
Okay so for me uh the Excel sheets don't
match okay that's what we expected and
you can see here it is saying Excel file
uh this does not match with this uh and
it will also tell the cell mismatch in
email so this is the reference value in
this cell
a49 is this and Target there is no value
in cell a49 so clearly it is specifying
uh with cells are not matching in your
Excel sheets okay the same result
will also be available in this um sheet
okay uh Let me refresh this just in
case okay and uh when I open this you
will see the same results what we saw on
the log info is recorded here as well
okay just for reporting purpose so you
can see here our value in this is not
matching with this value in this
particular cell okay and similarly you
will get results for all the uh
comparison which you have done for these
two particular uh Excel sheets okay so
that's how easy it is uh to compare to
excel sheets as I said you can do a lot
more um using this Excel engine modules
which are present in the tbx we'll see
that uh in a later session um how you
can steer different Excel sheets create
different values or open them save them
delete update so all kind of operations
you can perform on the exual seats okay
so that's all for this particular video
hope you enjoyed it and you learned
something new today uh keep watching our
videos uh at our Channel and don't
forget to subscribe as lots more videos
are coming up on tosa and other
automation tools this will uh help you
keep learning tosa in a most efficient
manner so until the next video uh keep
watching and keep learning we'll see you
in the next video